A Guide to the Records of Western State Hospital, 1825-2000
Library of Virginia
- Series IV. Patient Records, 1826-2001., Extent: 5.5 cubic feet of records and 189 volumes.
  - Series IV., Subseries F. Lists, 1828-1949.
    - Applicants/Patients by County, undated.
      Contains two lists of applicants and patients by county of origin. Both lists are undated, but appear to be pre-20th century. The first list book contains varying amounts of personal information about the patients such as sex, age, ability to pay, and health. In addition to listing applicants or patients by county, the second book contains lists of patients on each ward of the hospital.
      - List of Applicants/Patients by County, undated. (Volume 303)
      - List of Applicants/Patients by County, undated. (Volume 304)
    - Annual Lists, 1828-1907.
      Contains ledgers featuring lists of patients present at Western State Hospital during the course of a given year. The annual lists contain the patient's admission number, name, occupation, date of admission, sex, age, social relation, education, nativity, place of residence, number of attacks, cause of illness and its duration, date of removal or death, cause of death, and at times, notes about family medical history. The hospital used calendar years until September 1847, when they switched to a fiscal year format that began on 1 October and ran until 30 September of the following year. The annual lists for 1878-1907 are numbered and it appears that the first through sixth volumes are missing, since the numbering begins at volume seven. Annual List #29 (1900-1901) is also missing. In the first volume, patient information for the years 1828-1830 is recorded in admission register format, but it is recorded in annual list format for the remaining years, 1831-1845. (It is possible that this volume could have started out as the first admission register, with its information transferred to that ledger at a later date). Clothing inventory lists for patients and servants during 1830-1831 are also included in this volume. Additional information on clothing and linen inventories can be found in Series III. Financial Records, Subseries L. Supply Inventories. The final volume (1910-1913) contains three alphabetical lists of patients present during July 1910, January 1911, and January 1913. The annual lists contain much of the same information found in the biennial lists and admission registers, so researchers should utilize all three types of records.
      - 1828-1845. (Volume 305)
      - 1845-1846; 1854-1855. (Volume 306)
      - #7, 1878-1879. (Volume 307)
      - #8, 1879-1880. (Volume 308)
      - #9, 1880-1881. (Volume 309)
      - #10, 1881-1882. (Volume 310)
      - #11, 1882-1883. (Volume 311)
      - #12, 1883-1884. (Volume 312)
      - #13, 1884-1885. (Volume 313)
      - #14, 1885-1886. (Volume 314)
      - #15, 1886-1887. (Volume 315)
      - #16, 1887-1888. (Volume 316)
      - #17, 1888-1889. (Volume 317)
      - #18, 1889-1890. (Volume 318)
      - #19, 1890-1891. (Volume 319)
      - #20, 1891-1892. (Volume 320)
      - #21, 1892-1893. (Volume 321)
      - #22, 1893-1894. (Volume 322)
      - #23, 1894-1895. (Volume 323)
      - #24, 1895-1896. (Volume 324)
      - #25, 1896-1897. (Volume 325)
      - #26, 1897-1898. (Volume 326)
      - #27, 1898-1899. (Volume 327)
      - #28, 1899-1900. (Volume 328)
      - #30, 1901-1902. (Volume 329)
      - #31, 1902-1903. (Volume 330)
      - #32, 1903-1904. (Volume 331)
      - #33, 1904-1905. (Volume 332)
      - #34, 1905-1906. (Volume 333)
      - #35, 1906-1907. (Volume 334)
      - 1910-1913. (Volume 342)
    - Biennial Lists, 1855-1879.
      Contains volumes featuring lists of patients present at Western State Hospital during the course of two fiscal years, October 1 through September 30. The biennial lists contain information including the patient's admission number, name, sex, age, social relation, occupation, education, nativity, place of residence, number of admissions, number of attacks, cause of illness and its form, age at time of attack, admission date, removal date, amount of time spent in the asylum, duration of illness, condition upon removal or death, as well as the patient's condition and prospects for recovery if he or she continued to remain hospitalized. Some of the volumes also contain tables of statistical information compiled from the lists. Tables include documentation of admission numbers, discharges, deaths, civil condition (marital status), age at onset of insanity, and counties of origin. Often a chart covering admissions from 1828 to the date of the report was also included. One unique table is found in the biennial list for 1869-1871, which includes a list of rejected applicants. The biennial lists contain much of the same information found in the annual lists and admission registers.
      - 1855-1869. (Volume 335)
      - #1, 1867-1869. (Volume 336)
      - #2, 1869-1871. (Volume 337)
      - #3, 1871-1873. (Volume 338)
      - #4, 1873-1875. (Volume 339)
      - #5, 1875-1877. (Volume 340)
      - #6, 1877-1879. (Volume 341)
    - Censuses, 1916-1949.
      Restricted: Patient censuses that are less than 125 years old. Please see reference staff if you wish to view a register that has a date range that encompasses both unrestricted and restricted content. Contains volumes featuring information about patient admissions, furloughs, deaths, discharges, and elopements (escapes). All but one of the ledgers are divided according to patient sex, with sections for each action taken. The sections contain lists of patients by month and year. The final census (1948-1949) is divided by day and contains the same information, but for both male and female patients. The title of "patient census" may be misleading since only those patients who were admitted, furloughed, discharged, or those who died or escaped are listed. There are many overlapping dates, but because of the similarity in content, these volumes were included here together. It is unknown why the dates overlap, nor is there an explanation why there are more volumes devoted to female patients than to male patients. Researchers should be aware that many similarities exist between the censuses and the ward lists, found in the section below.
      - Male Patients.
        - 1917-1926. (Volume 343)
        - 1926-1932. (Volume 344)
      - Female Patients.
        - 1916-1931. (Volume 345)
        - 1929-1932. (Volume 346)
        - 1931-1939. (Volume 347)
        - 1932-1935. (Volume 348)
        - 1935-1938. (Volume 349)
        - 1938-1939. (Volume 350)
        - 1938-1940. (Volume 351)
        - 1939-1947. (Volume 352)
        - 1944-1947 [Also contains an attendant sign-out sheet, 1926-1930]. (Volume 353)
      - Male and Female Patients.
        - 1948-1949. (Volume 354)
    - Ward Lists, 1886-1910.
      Contains volumes with lists of patients according to the ward on which they resided. Patient names and dates of transfer, furlough, death, or discharge are provided, but only if such action took place during that particular year. These volumes may be earlier versions of the patient censuses, since the ward lists contain much the same type of information, but in a different format. In the earliest pages of the first ledger (1886-1910) there are lists of patient by ward, but little additional information. By 1893, notes about furloughs are included in the lists, as well as identifying information such as age, weight, and residency. Also included in this first volume are recipes, definitions of diseases, and a list of attendants who refused to remain quarantined during a small pox outbreak in 1895. Male wards are numbered and female wards are lettered. All of the volumes, except for one, are separated according to patient sex. Due to the similarities between the censuses and ward lists, researchers should consult both sets of records.
      - Male Patients.
        - 1886-1910. (Volume 355)
        - 1904-1906. (Volume 356)
        - 1905-1908. (Volume 357)
        - 1907-1909. (Volume 358)
      - Female Patients.
        - 1906-1910. (Volume 359)
      - Male and Female Patients.
        - 1905-1907. (Volume 360)
  - Series IV., Subseries G. Medical Records, 1897-1980.
    Contains several different types of patient medical records that describe treatment administered at Western State Hospital including clinical and operating room registers, dental records, and weight registers. This subseries also contains records related to controverial procedures such as patient sterilization and transorbital lobotomies. Researchers should note that additional treatment information can be found in Subseries C. Case Books. The medical records are part of accessions 41404 and 41253.
    - Clinic Register, 1964-1967.
      Restricted: Patient medical records that are less than 125 years old. No viewing, photocopying, or redaction of medical records less than 125 years of age is allowed. Please see reference staff if you wish to view a register that has a date range that encompasses both unrestricted and restricted content. Contains one register detailing treatments performed on patients at various clinics at Western State Hospital. The records are divided according to the type of clinic including dermatology, general medicine, neurology, gynecology, immunizations, tuberculosis, otolaryngology, prenatal, surgery, psychiatry and urology. The records contain the patient's name, ward of residence, health problem, treatment given, and doctor's notations.
      - Clinic Register, 1964-1967. (Volume 361)
    - Dental Treatment Registers, 1919-1940.
      Restricted: Patient medical records that are less than 125 years old. No viewing, photocopying, or redaction of medical records less than 125 years of age is allowed. Please see reference staff if you wish to view a register that has a date range that encompasses both unrestricted and restricted content. Contains dental treatment ledgers that are arranged chronologically by day. Each day contains a list of patients and the dental treatments they received.
      - , 1919. (Volume 362)
      - , 1922-1923. (Volume 363)
      - 1923-1924. (Volume 364)
      - 1924-1925. (Volume 365)
      - 1925-1928. (Volume 366)
      - 1928-1930. (Volume 367)
      - 1930-1932. (Volume 368)
      - 1932-1933. (Volume 369)
      - 1933-1935. (Volume 370)
      - 1937-1940. (Volume 371)
    - Electroencephalography (EEG) Ledgers, 1947-1973.
      Restricted: EEG Records that are less than 125 years old (Volume 373). No viewing, photocopying, or redaction of medical records less than 125 years of age is allowed. Please see reference staff if you wish to view this register once the date range encompasses both unrestricted and restricted content. Contains a ledger of physician notes on electroencephalography (EEG), as well as a ledger of patient records documenting the administration of EEGs at Western State Hospital. The first volume contains various notes and charts on the subject of electroencephalography. The second volume contains records of actual EEG treatments administered on patients. The entries include date, patient name, sex, clinical diagnosis, and notes about the test results.
      - EEG Notes, 1947. (Volume 372)
      - EEG Records, 1953-1973. (Volume 373)
    - Fit/Seizure Registers, 1897-1946.
      Restricted: Patient medical records that are less than 125 years old. No viewing, photocopying, or redaction of medical records less than 125 years of age is allowed. Please see reference staff if you wish to view a register that has a date range that encompasses both unrestricted and restricted content. Contains two ledgers which document fits and seizures experienced by patients at Western State Hospital. Within the earliest volume, each patient has a page featuring the date and number of seizures endured. The volume has an index, but the entries usually contain only the patient's last name. The later volume is arranged in much the same manner, except that it only contains information about female patients.
      - Record of Fits, 1897-1899. (Volume 374)
      - Record of Seizures, 1945-1946. (Volume 375)
    - Operating Room Registers, 1940-1980.
      Restricted: Patient medical records that are less than 125 years old. No viewing, photocopying, or redaction of medical records less than 125 years of age is allowed. Please see reference staff if you wish to view a register that has a date range that encompasses both unrestricted and restricted content. Contains ledgers with chronologically arranged entries for operation procedures performed at Western State Hospital. The entries note the patient's name, the type of operation and anesthesia used, as well as the names of doctors and nurses present. Some volumes also include notations as to the patient's age, next-of-kin contact information, the ward in which he or she resided, and whether there were complications during the operation.
      - 1940-1958. (Volume 376)
      - 1959-1963. (Volume 377)
      - 1963-1967. (Volume 378)
      - 1967. (Volume 379)
      - 1969-1972. (Volume 380)
      - 1972-1980. (Volume 381)
    - Sterilization Records, 1924-1968.
      Restricted: Documents containing patient medical information that are less than 125 years old. No viewing, photocopying, or redaction of medical records less than 125 years of age is allowed. Contains one volume and three files documenting sterilization procedures performed at Western State Hospital. The files document the steps taken before and after the surgery was performed. The register features only female patients, and lists the patient's age, mental affliction, information pertaining to the surgery, any problems the doctors encountered, and how well the patient recovered. Additional sterilization medical records for both male and female patients can be found in the operating room registers, found in a previous section. Researchers should also note that general information on sterlization including articles and court cases, as well as superintendent's correspondence related to the procedure, can be found in Series I. Administrative Records, Subseries H. General Files and Ledgers, 20th Century Files.
      - Interrogatories for Sterilization, 1924-1928. (Box 224, Folder 1)
      - Notices that Sexual Sterilization Has Been Performed, 1949-1968. (Box 224, Folder 2)
      - Petition for Sterilization, illegible date (possibly 1929). (Box 224, Folder 3)
      - Sterilization Operation Register, 1929-1931. (Volume 382)
    - Transorbital Lobotomy Records, 1950-1955.
      Restricted: Patient medical records that are less than 125 years old. No viewing, photocopying, or redaction of medical records less than 125 years of age is allowed. Contains medical and photographic records of patients who received transorbital lobotomies at Western State Hospital. The case book files were originally housed in an album and contain medical histories, photographs of patients before, during, and after their operations, and written descriptions of each surgery. The contents of the album are arranged in their original order (loosely alphabetical), and the photographs have been sleeved for their protection. The other files contain post-operation reports and patient follow-up information. Transorbital lobotomies were performed by inserting an icepick into the eye socket and tapping it with a hammer to break through the bone. The pick was then used to "stir" the frontal lobe. It was believed that this operation alleviated many forms of mental illness. Most of the operations were performed by Dr. Walter Freeman, who is famous for introducing and promoting the use of transorbital lobotomy to treat mental illness in the United States. Dr. Freeman visited Western State Hospital several times over a four year period. During his short visits he interviewed perspective candidates and performed multiple surgeries. Western State Hospital discontinued the use of Dr. Freeman's services once the antipyschotic drug thorazine was introduced. Additional medical information on transorbital lobotomies can be found in the Operating Room Registers in a previous section. Researchers should also note that general information on lobotomies, as well as superintendent's correspondence related to the procedure, can be found in Series I. Administrative Records, Subseries H. General Files and Ledgers, 20th Century Files.
      - Case Book, 1950-1954. (Box 224, Folder 4)
      - Case Book, 1950-1954. (Box 224, Folder 5)
      - Case Book, 1950-1954. (Box 224, Folder 6)
      - Case Book, 1950-1954. (Box 224, Folder 7)
      - Case Book, 1950-1954. (Box 224, Folder 8)
      - Case Book, 1950-1954. (Box 224, Folder 9)
      - Case Book, 1950-1954. (Box 224, Folder 10)
      - Case Book, 1950-1954. (Box 224, Folder 11)
      - Case Book, 1950-1954. (Box 224, Folder 12)
      - Case Book, 1950-1954. (Box 224, Folder 13)
      - Case Book, 1950-1954. (Box 224, Folder 14)
      - Case Book, 1950-1954. (Box 224, Folder 15)
      - Case Book, 1950-1954. (Box 224, Folder 16)
      - Case Book, 1950-1954. (Box 225, Folder 1)
      - Case Book, 1950-1954. (Box 225, Folder 2)
      - Patient Follow-Up Sheets, 1952 Operations, undated (circa 1955). (Box 225, Folder 3)
      - Patient Follow-Up Sheets, 1953 Operations, undated (circa 1955). (Box 225, Folder 4)
      - Patient Follow-Up Sheets, 1954 Operations, undated (circa 1955). (Box 225, Folder 5)
      - Post-Lobotomy Reports, 1952-1955. (Box 225, Folder 6)
    - Vital Signs Register, 1954-1961.
      Restricted: Patient medical records that are less than 125 years old. No viewing, photocopying, or redaction of medical records less than 125 years of age is allowed. Please see reference staff if you wish to view this register once the date range encompasses both unrestricted and restricted content. Contains one volume containing records of vital signs for female patients. Each day vital signs were recorded at very specific intervals. There is little information to indicate which signs were being taken, but it appears that body temperature and possibly pulse were recorded, along with another unidentifiable number. Judging by the limited number of patient names found in the register, it is likely that this volume is devoted to one particular ward and not the entire female patient population.
      - 1954-1961. (Volume 383)
    - Weight Registers, 1940-1961.
      Restricted: Patient medical records that are less than 125 years old. No viewing, photocopying, or redaction of medical records less than 125 years of age is allowed. Please see reference staff if you wish to view a register that has a date range that encompasses both unrestricted and restricted content. Contains volumes that document the results of periodic patient weigh-ins. It appears that the patients were weighed approximately four times each month. The registers are designed as spreadsheets so one can easily trace a particular patient's record.
      - Male Patients.
        - Ward 21, 1940-1948. (Volume 384)
        - Ward 6, 1942-1948 [Also contains census information, 1940]. (Volume 385)
        - Ward 5, 1942-1948. (Volume 386)
      - Female Patients.
        - Possibly Ward T, 1947-1954 [Also contains census information, 1946-1947]. (Volume 387)
        - Possibly Ward T, 1954-1961. (Volume 388)
  - Series IV., Subseries H. Personal Effects Registers, 1855-1976.
    Contains three different types of records used to keep track of each patient's personal belongings during his or her stay at Western State Hospital. The receiving books document the various clothing and personal items that arrived with each patient, as well as any additional items sent to the patient while he or she was hospitalized. The valuables ledgers document items of particular value brought with each patient. Researchers should note that the volumes in Series V. Report Books and Other Registers, Subseries K. Out Books also contain information about possessions (mostly clothes) that were checked out to patients by ward attendants. The personal effects records are part of accession 41404.
    - Receiving Books, 1855-1945.
      Restricted: Registers containing patient names and information that are less than 125 years old. Please see reference staff if you wish to view a register that has a date range that encompasses both unrestricted and restricted content. Contains volumes featuring information about clothing and other personal articles belonging to Western State Hospital patients. The receiving books were used to keep track of items received with the patient upon admission, additional articles sent from home, and those bought for the patient while he or she was living at the hospital. The earliest two volumes chronologically list when clothing and other items were received and bought for the patients, with no division between the sexes. The later volumes are divided by sex, but information is not recorded chronologically. An index is usually present at the front of these later volumes. The receiving books serve as ongoing inventories of items each patient accumulated during short periods of time, usually two or three years. However, the most modern receiving books are arranged differently. In these volumes, each page represents a day of the year and contains a list of all items received, as well as the name of the recipient. There are no indices, nor are the volumes divided by ward. For an unknown reason, the dates overlap in several of the receiving books, and gaps in time exist as well. The foldered material was originally found in metal binders and was removed for preservation purposes.
      Arranged according to patient sex, and then chronologically within.
      - Male and Female Patients.
        - 1855-1879. (Volume 389)
        - 1867-1875. (Volume 390)
      - Male Patients.
        - 1857-1868. (Volume 433)
        - 1879-1884. (Volume 391)
        - 1926-1928. (Volume 392)
        - 1928-1930. (Volume 393)
        - 1933-1934. (Volume 394)
        - 1935. (Box 225, Folder 7)
        - 1943. (Box 225, Folder 8)
        - 1943. (Box 225, Folder 9)
        - 1944. (Box 225, Folder 10)
        - 1944. (Box 225, Folder 11)
        - 1944. (Box 225, Folder 12)
        - 1944. (Box 225, Folder 13)
        - 1944. (Box 225, Folder 14)
        - 1944. (Box 225, Folder 15)
        - 1945. (Box 225, Folder 16)
        - 1945. (Box 225, Folder 17)
        - 1945. (Box 226, Folder 1)
        - 1945. (Box 226, Folder 2)
        - 1945. (Box 226, Folder 3)
        - 1945. (Box 226, Folder 4)
        - 1945. (Box 226, Folder 5)
      - Female Patients.
        - #1, 1886-1918. (Volume 395)
        - #2, 1903-1921. (Volume 396)
        - #3, 1909-1921. (Volume 397)
        - #4, 1910-1921. (Volume 398)
        - #5, 1915-1921. (Volume 399)
        - 1918-1922. (Volume 400)
        - 1921-1924. (Volume 401)
        - 1923-1926. (Volume 402)
        - 1924-1927. (Volume 403)
        - 1926-1928. (Volume 404)
        - 1927-1929. (Volume 405)
        - 1928-1931. (Volume 406)
        - 1929-1931. (Volume 407)
        - 1930-1931. (Volume 408)
        - 1931-1932. (Volume 409)
        - 1932-1933. (Volume 410)
        - 1933-1934. (Volume 411)
        - 1934-1936. (Volume 412)
        - 1935-1937. (Volume 413)
        - 1936-1939. (Volume 414)
        - 1936-1942. (Volume 415)
        - 1938-1942. (Volume 416)
        - 1943-1945. (Volume 417)
        - 1945. (Box 226, Folder 6)
        - 1945. (Box 226, Folder 7)
        - 1945. (Box 226, Folder 8)
        - 1945. (Box 226, Folder 9)
    - Valuables Registers, 1885-1976.